Okay,
we start today's דף כ"ט. Daf Kaf-Tet. We start with a new
פרק, Perek, very bottom of כ"א עמוד ב'. Kaf-Aleph Amud Bet. Now
we had last פרק Perek we had seen all the issues about
ולד Vlad and תמורה Tmura of all the קרבנות Korbanot except חטאת.
Chatat. חטאת Chatat is the one which is devoted its own פרק
Perek for reasons that we'll hear. I know, we know there's this
category of חטאת מתה Chatat Meita and we normally are familiar that
there are five things in the category, but we're going to see
in our משנה Mishna that it's not so clear exactly how those
five are defined. So let's take a look. ולד חטאת, Vlad Chatat,
ותמורת חטאת, u'Tmura Chatat, וחטאת שמתו בעליה. v'Chatat she'meitu ba'aleha. So those
three are clear. The child of a חטאת, Chatat, a תמורה Tmura
of a חטאת, Chatat, or a חטאת Chatat that the owners have
died, so it can no longer serve its atonement purpose. In all
those cases, ימותו. yamutu. You have to basically lock them up, let
them die. Okay, so now there normally are two others that are
added to this list, which is כיפרו בעליה באחר, kiperu ba'aleha b'acher,
whether the owners got some atonement through some other way, and עבר
שנתה, avar shnata, it's no longer a year old.
So, נתכפרו בעליה באחר. nitkapru ba'aleha b'acher. So let's take a look.
We're now going to look at those, but they're going to be
qualified in a particular way. ושעבר
שנתה, v'she'avar shnata, if it's more than a year old, you've sanctified
it when it was a year, now it's more than a year
old and you only bring it when it's one year old. ושאבדה
ונמצאת בעלת מום, v'she'avda v'nimtza ba'alat mum, or it was lost and
then when it was discovered it had a blemish. Interesting, that that
idea of getting a blemish got introduced. Let's read it and then
I'll discuss it. אם משיכפרו הבעלים תמות. im mishe'kiperu ba'alim tamut. Now
there's a very key question here of whether it's משיכפרו הבעלים mishe'kiperu
ba'alim or כיפרו הבעלים. kiperu ba'alim. רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both
say the גרסא girsa אם כיפרו הבעלים תמות. im kiperu ba'alim tamut.
What's the difference? The difference is that we're going to see in
the next משנה, Mishna, which we'll get to today, that there is
a debate when we have this principle about כיפרו בעליה באחר, kiperu
ba'aleha b'acher, that the
owners used another קרבן, Korban, whether that applies only if it was
lost, then they got their atonement, and then they found the one
that was lost. So when this one that was lost was found,
they had already been atoned for. That's the more obvious case, that
then the הלכה Halacha is that it die. But what if it
was found before they sanctified another one, then they found the first
one, and then they went ahead and they brought one? So that
it was found before they atoned, but then they used another one
to atone for. So there there's a debate whether the first one
dies or not. Because whatever, because when I don't know why. Okay,
these are all relatively arbitrary. But the point is that there it
was in the first case it was clearly not in the picture
when the owners were נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru b'acher, when it was found
it was already, when you were dealing with it, it was already
a status of נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru b'acher. Here when you were dealing
with it and you found it first, it had a potential of
being brought. And since it had a potential of being brought, it's
never considered to be the same degree sort of rejected.
So you wait until it gets a
מום mum and then you redeem it and then you use and
then well actually yeah that they you
right because a חטאת, Chatat, מותר חטאת motar Chatat
is קרב... karev... if you have מותר חטאת, motar Chatat, I had
it before, I'm sorry. I'll get back to you in a second
about that. Okay, let me just finish this point.
So anyway, so that's that הלכה. Halacha. Now let me just finish
this point, let me just finish this for you.
Yeah, yeah. So מותר חטאת motar Chatat when you have a case,
right, when you have a case that is not a חטאת מתה,
Chatat Meita, then it's the same as an אשם, Asham, that the
extra money goes to an עולה. Ola. Okay, fine.
נדבת ציבור... Nedavat tzibur...
yeah,
so okay. So anyway, let's just see this. So fine. So that's
the basic first הלכה, Halacha, which is that when it's נתכפרו באחר,
nitkapru b'acher, there's a debate about whether it was found after they
after the owners brought another one or before. Okay, that's a normal
case. So therefore, if your גרסא girsa here is אם משיכפרו הבעלים
תמות, im mishe'kiperu ba'alim tamut, which means if it's found after they
were atoned for, that limits the case to when it was found
afterwards. And that limits the case to the position of רבי Rebbe
who says that the only time a חטאת Chatat is מתה Meita
is if it was found after the atonement was brought. Okay, the
fact that רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot switch the גרסא girsa to
say אם כיפרו הבעלים תמות, im kiperu ba'alim tamut, that even if
it was found earlier, once the owners brought another one it will
die, okay, as that big difference between אם משיכפרו. im mishe'kiperu. Since
there's a debate, as I said, whether, you know, it's only הלכה
Halacha only applies if it was found afterwards, if your גרסא girsa
is אם משיכפרו, im mishe'kiperu, it means it was found afterwards, and
that would limit it. If it says אם כיפרו הבעלים, im kiperu
ba'alim, or אם כיפרו הבעלים, im kiperu ba'alim,
if afterwards they got כפרה, kappara, means even if it was found
before. And I'm going to read this by the way רש"י Rashi
does because there's a whole question רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot how to
read it, but רש"י Rashi basically says like this, and this is
going to come up a lot in the גמרא. Gemara.
If even according to the position we're going to see later on
of רבי Rebbe that says it only has a status of חטאת
מתה Chatat Meita when it's found after the owners are atoned for,
only if it's found later after the atonement, in this case when
it was found before the atonement, רבי Rebbe would agree it's תמות
tamut if in addition it has this additional problem of being a
בעל מום. ba'al mum. And רש"י's Rashi general approach is as follows...
double problem somehow that leads to the status of it being תמות.
tamus. תוספות Tosfos doesn't really agree with that, but we're going to
read the גמרא Gemara like רש"י. Rashi. So what do we have
now? What we have is we have the three standard חטאות המתות.
chatos hamessos. You have lost חטאת, chatas, תמורת חטאת, tmuras chatat, מתו
בעליה. meisu ba'aleha. Then you have the other two. You have עברה
שנתה avrah shnasah and שאבדה וכיפרו בעלים באחרת. she'avdah ve'kiperu ba'alim be'acheres.
And normally we would think עברה שנתה avrah shnasah would be enough
by itself. But here the משנה Mishnah is telling us no, that
עברה שנתה avrah shnasah needs also כיפרו בעלים באחרת kiperu ba'alim be'acheres
that the owners used another one instead of it, כיפרו בעלים באחרת.
kiperu ba'alim be'acheres. We would normally think one minute that כיפרו בעלים
באחרת kiperu ba'alim be'acheres would be enough by itself, but here it's
got another problem of being a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So actually
what you have here is you have two things going on. You
have let's say you have that it is more than a year
old or that it's a בעל מום ba'al mum and that the
owners got another atonement.
You have a double problem.
And the reason for the double problem, at least one of the
things the way רש"י Rashi understands it is, is because therefore it
becomes תמות tamus even before even if it was found before they
brought the other atonement. So even though there's a debate whether that's
תמות tamus here that it's a double problem, it was found and
you had both and you still brought the other one, then it
is תמות tamus because it has two problems. It was כיפרו באחר
kiperu be'acher and it was more than a year old or כיפרו
באחר kiperu be'acher and it was בעל מום. ba'al mum. Charlie first.
So there's another possibility. You designate a חטאת, chatas, you designate a
second חטאת, chatas, then you find the first one and you bring
the first one. Right. What happens to the second?
Right. So according to well we'll see. I mean according to רבי,
Rebbe, I'm not sure according to רבי Rebbe whether you have the
option of bringing of bringing the first one since he says that
the הלכה halacha is is that once you've designated another and then
it was אבדה, avdah, it's תמות. tamus. So I think according to
רבי, Rebbe, according to the חכמים Chachamim you're right, you can bring
either and the other one as mentioned before goes to an עולה.
olah. But I have to I have to check according to רבי
Rebbe you even have that option because רבי Rebbe says it basically
has the הלכה halacha of תמות tamus once it's been lost. Yeah,
good question.
So if you have like two of these problems, עברה שנתה avrah
shnasah and אבדה, avdah, but not necessarily כיפרו, kiperu, then that still
wouldn't be enough? You need these two problems be one of the
problems and כיפרו, kiperu, right? Yeah. Yeah, exactly. And then let's say
like you know and just to complicate this, let's say you have
a חטאת chatas that gets mixed up with another one that's not
תמות. tamus. What do you do?
We're going to have the גמרא Gemara is going to talk about
a case of תערובת. ta'aroves. Yeah.
As for one was recovery, does that mean slaughter in the sense
like שחיטה shechitah where you go through all the ברכות brachos or
could you just shoot it down?
No, neither. It's קדשים kodashim so you can't do anything active. You
have to let it die.
So you don't actively you lock
it up and you let it starve.
I see, but it cannot be just shot another way other than
שחיטה? shechitah? Correct. Correct.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Now the משנה Mishnah
goes on. Now the משנה Mishnah ties it back to the תורה
Torah הלכה halacha because now that you have a חטאת chatas that's
supposed to die, so it's not any it doesn't have קדושה kedushah
that it will ever make it to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. This animal
won't go to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you're not going to redeem it
at any so any of its value won't go to the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So because it's never headed to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it or
its value or its קדושה, kedushah, therefore there are certain implications of
that. אינה עושה תמורה. einah osah tmurah. You cannot make a תמורה
tmurah with it. Like you can make a תמורה tmurah with the
בעל מום, ba'al mum, but that at least the money is eventually
going to go to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Here you cannot make a
תמורה tmurah with it because it will never head to the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. One wonders actually,
I'm just asking myself now, what would be the הלכה halacha of
a בכור bechor or מעשר ma'aser that was a בעל מום? ba'al
mum? So that also is never going to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Maybe
that also you can't do a תמורה. tmurah. I don't know, it's
an interesting question. Anyway, לא נהנין, lo nehenin, I would assume that
would be the הלכה. halacha. But let's see. לא נהנין ולא מועלין.
lo nehenin velo mo'alin. Not only that, although you're not allowed to
derive benefit, you do not transgress the biblical prohibition of מעילה. me'ilah.
Since this is never ultimately going to the temple or going to
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's just going to be let die, therefore you
do not transgress מעילה me'ilah because it is never really going to
be fully the temple's. And if until so those are some implications
of it being תמות. tamus.
So you can't use it though.
Can't use it, לא נהנין. lo nehenin. ואם עד שלא כיפרו הבעלים.
ve'im ad shelo kiperu haba'alim. Now let's say you found the lost
one and you have not yet brought the other animal as a
קרבן. korban. Okay, so you lost one then you found it and
it was a בעל מום ba'al mum or you had something that
was עברה שנתה avrah shnasah that went was over a year and
you have yet to bring the next קרבן. korban. So if you
have yet to bring the other קרבן korban instead of it, this
is not yet a case of נתכפרו באחר. niskafru be'acher. Okay, so
what's the הלכה? halacha? It was lost but you haven't yet atoned
for it in another way. So then the הלכה halacha is fine,
תרעה עד שתסתאב ותמכר ויביא בדמיה אחרת. tira'eh ad she'tista'ev ve'timacher ve'yavi
bidameha acheres. Then you wait till it gets a מום, mum, you
transfer the value as long as you haven't like brought another one,
just you know transfer the value and bring the חטאת chatas that
you have to bring. ועושה תמורה ומועלין בה. ve'osah tmurah u'mo'alin bah.
Then it has a full status of a חטאת. chatas. So I
lost my animal, I found it, it has a מום. mum. What
do you do with a חטאת chatas with a מום? mum? A
חטאת chatas with a מום, mum, you transfer the value and you
buy another חטאת chatas and you bring the one you're obligated. What
do you do for a חטאת chatas that's more than a year
old? You transfer the value, well you wait till it gets a
מום mum because being a year old doesn't count as a מום,
mum, we already had that discussion before, and then you went go
ahead and you transfer the value and you buy another and you
use another one. So if you don't have נתכפרו באחר, niskafru be'acher,
you still have your options open here, you know, you just transfer
the value. But once it's נתכפרו באחר, niskafru be'acher, then you've got
these problems. So I want to So I want to point out
though the interesting thing that emerges from our משנה mishna is we
normally think that עבר שנתו avar shnaso by itself, because it's in
that list of the five things of חטאת המתה, chatas hameisah, our
משנה mishna makes it clear that even when it's more than a
year old, it's not a חטאת המתה chatas hameisah until the owners
have atoned elsewhere. Okay, so which in a way makes sense, because
why is עבר שנתו avar shnaso so significantly worse than a בעל
מום? baal mum? It's the same thing, I just can't use it,
right?
So why should it be bad? Let it get a מום mum
and redeem it, end of story. So really עבר שנתו avar shnaso
is really a subset of נתכפרו בעלים באחר, niskapru baalim beacher, that
they really because of that used another animal. That's at least the
way our משנה mishna has it. Yes.
There's just a question though, we say תרעה עד שיסתאב, tireh ad
sheyistaev, you know,
which is maybe fine with an עולה olah where you don't have
a time limit, but they have to bring a חטאת chatas sometimes,
you know what I mean? Like a נזיר, nazir, you know, so
do I have to wait for my כפרה kaparah to be fully
effective until this thing, you know, gets a מום? mum? It could
be ten years later. Like you know, say a יולדת, yoledes, can't
go to the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Yeah, I understand. It's a good question, you know, whether
you could do it על ידי גרמא al yedei grama maybe.
No, no, or can I like, you know, wink wink, bring another
one and then oh wait, this has to be המתה, hameisah, or
am I causing like...
Well, you could do that. You could do that and then you
make it into a חטאת המתה. chatas hameisah.
Right, so לכתחילה lechatchila I can do that?
That's a good question. Yeah, probably. I don't know. It's a good
question. I mean, I don't remember any discussion about not being able
to go ahead and bring the other one and create a חטאת
המתה, chatas hameisah, but it's a good thing, it's a good thing
you're thinking. Right. Okay, so it's a good point. I understand. Yeah,
it's a good point. All right, let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? Now the גמרא Gemara asks a
question which seems to be quite obvious,
so let's take a look. מאי טעמא לא תני להו גבי הדדי?
Mai taama lo sani lehu gabei hadadi? Why didn't it list all
of the five חטאת המתה chatas hameisah together? Why did it first
say three and then say the other two? So the answer is
obvious because there's different
הלכות. halachos. משום דהני פסיקא ליה והני לא פסיקא ליה. Mishum dehani
pesika lei vehani lo pesika lei. The first three, it's categorical. If
it's תמורת חטאת, tmuras chatas, ולד חטאת, velad chatas, or מתו בעליה,
meisu baaleha, it always is תמות. tamus. The last two, where it's
אבדה avdah
or עבר שנתו, avar shnaso, it's not all times. It's only when
then afterwards you brought another one for atonement. Okay, פסיקא ליה ולא
פסיקא ליה. Pesika lei velo pesika lei. So
למה לי למתנייה גבי מעילה למה לי למתנייה גבי תמורה? Lama li
lemasniyah gabei meilah lama li lemasniyah gabei tmura? We have another textual
question. This exact same משנה mishna appears here in מסכת תמורה Masechet
Tmura and it appears also in מסכת מעילה. Masechet Meilah. Now you
understand because what's the הלכה halacha of a חטאת chatas that has
to die? It's first of all there's no מעילה meilah and there's
no תמורה. tmura. So therefore the הלכה halacha applies to both מסכתות.
masechtos. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. It says we're doing
מעילה. meilah. So the גמרא Gemara said תנא הכא תמורה. Tana hacha
tmura. So here it's talking about תמורה. tmura. ואיידי דתנא תמורה תנא
נמי מעילה. Veaydi detana tmura tana nami meilah. And since it was
telling you the הלכה halacha is that it's not עושה תמורה, oseh
tmura, it also tells you that there's no מעילה. meilah.
Okay, and then the side has a slightly better גרסא girsa that
says ואיידי דתני גבי תמורה מעילה תני נמי גבי מעילה תמורה. Veaydi
detani gabei tmura meilah tani nami gabei meilah tmura. And since while
we're talking about תמורה tmura we mention מעילה, meilah, so we're going
to repeat the משנה mishna over there and talk about מעילה, meilah,
and since we're talking about מעילה meilah we're going to talk about
תמורה. tmura. Basically it's the same משנה mishna that's applicable in both
places. Okay, תנא נמי Tana nami so ואיידי דתני גבי מעילה מעילה
תני נמי תמורה. veaydi detani gabei meilah meilah tani nami tmura. Since
it's by מעילה meilah it's going to say the מעילה meilah part,
it's also going to say the תמורה. tmura. Fine. Now we get
to the back to the הלכה, halacha, now that we're done with
those textual issues. אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish Lakish: חטאת
שעברה שנתו
Chatas sheavrah
shnaso רואים אותה כאילו עומדת בבית הקברות ורועה. roim osah keilu omedes
beveit hakevaros veroeh. If you have a חטאת chatas that's a year
old, over a year, you look at it as though it's in
the cemetery, which means what? It's in a place where you don't
have access to it, so the כהן kohen can't get to it.
So it's as if it's in a place where there's no access
and you have to let it graze. Meaning it's not really a
problem in the animal itself, it's never going to lead to הלכה
halacha that it has to die. He seems to be denying completely
the הלכה halacha of עבר שנתו, avar shnaso, okay, and he basically
just says fine, you don't have access to it, so you wait
for it to get a מום, mum, but there's never going to
actually be considered a problem of תמות. tamus.
I think they disagree with the...
Let's take a look at what the... Yeah, I think the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: תנן, Tnan, let's look at our משנה. mishna. שאברה שנתו
ואבדה ונמצאת בעלת מום אם אחר שכיפרו בעלים מתה. Sheavrah shnaso veavdah
venimtzes baalas mum im achar shekiperu baalim meisah. So
our משנה mishna says at least if you combine the idea that
it was more than a year old and they were already used
and then beforehand or afterwards, whatever, they already were atoned with something
else, that it's תמות. tamus. So obviously if you combine the עבר
שנתו avar shnaso with נתכפרו בעלים באחר, niskafru baalim beacher, it's תמות.
tamus. So how does that work for you? You seem to make
a categorical statement that it's never תמות. tamus. So the גמרא Gemara
says תיובתא דריש לקיש, Tyufta deReish Lakish, so that's a contradiction to
Reish Lakish. אמר לך ריש לקיש, Amar lach Reish Lakish, Reish Lakish
will say back to you: כי קתני רישא מתה אאבדה ונמצאת בעלת
מום. Ki kasni reisha meisah aavdah venimtzes baalas mum. Ah,
when the משנה mishna said, because the משנה mishna reads, you know,
it's a funny, it's not, you know, it's not exactly clear where
to put the commas in the משנה, mishna, right? It could be
the way Reish Lakish is reading it: ושעברה
שנתו, vesheavrah shnaso, period. Now of course the question is what's the
הלכה halacha of עבר שנתו? avar shnaso? Then he says: ושאבדה ונמצאת
בעלת מום אם שכיפרו בעלים תמות. veshaavdah venimtzes baalas mum im shekiperu
baalim tamus. So the whole discussion at the end about if the
owners were atoned and it dies, if they don't they don't die,
is all going on the scenario that it was lost and that
it had a בעל מום. baal mum. Okay, and that it was
found and they were already atoned. But the category of that it
was over a year old, that's not being addressed at the end
of the משנה. mishna. So the question is, so then what what
is it doing in the משנה? mishna? What's the הלכה? halacha? It's
just a phrase sitting in the middle of nowhere. Right Then it
says, if it's more than a year old or was lost found
a מום mum *mum*, and then they got another atonement, then it
dies. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* is saying, no, no,
no, this last thing about it dies if it was, if they
got atonement elsewhere, that's only on the very final case when it
was lost and found and had a מום mum *mum*. Not on
this fourth case of עיבור שנה ibur shanah. *ibur shnaso*. So then
what's it doing in the משנה mishnah *Mishna*? It's not part of
the first הלכה halacha *halacha*, it's not part of the last הלכה
halacha, *halacha*. What's the הלכה halacha *halacha*? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
is going to ask that. Let's take a look. קתני רישא מתה
metah. *K'tani reisha mesa*, when does it say that they die? אבדה
avda. ונמצאת בעלת מום ba'alat mum, *Avda v'nimtzas ba'alas mum*. Only in
the case when it was lost and it was found to be
a בעל מום ba'al mum, *ba'al mum*. אם הכי *Im hachi*, if
that's true, אימא סיפא *eima seifa*, let's look at the very end
of the משנה mishna *Mishna*. אם עד שלא כיפרו הבעלים *Im ad
shelo kiperu haba'alim*, if it was found before the owners were atoned,
the end of our משנה mishnah, *Mishna*, what's the הלכה halacha *halacha*?
תרעה עד שתסתאב *Tira ad shetista'ev*. Wait till it gets a מום
mum *mum* and then redeem it, right? You found the animal that
was lost, wait for it to get a מום mum *mum*, redeem
it because you haven't brought another one, use that money for a
חטאת chatat *chatas*. But one minute, if the whole case at the
end is talking only about the case that it had a מום
mum. *mum*, so what does it mean wait for it to get
a מום mum *mum*? ואי בעלת מום ba'alat mum, *V'i ba'alas mum*,
if you're saying it already had a מום mum *mum*, הא מסתאבא
וקיימא *ha mistarva v'kaima*, it already is spoiled, meaning it already has
a מום mum, *mum*. Right? So do you understand? Meaning, there are
two cases at the end: more than a year old and lost
and found and had a מום mum, *mum*. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
*Reish Lakish* is trying to cut out the more than a year
old. And he says we're only talking about lost found had a
מום mum *mum*. If you were atoned for, then it's מתה metah,
*mesa*. If you weren't atoned for, wait for it to get a
מום mum *mum*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, once you've cut
out the case of more than a year old, you can't say
wait for it to get a מום mum, *mum* because you said
you're only talking about the case where it already has a מום
mum *mum*. So how could that make sense? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, אמר רבא amar Rava. הכי קאמר *Amar Rava hachi ka'amar*.
So here's how we're going to really try to squeeze this in.
In the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not going to be
satisfied, so don't worry. It says שאבדה ונמצאת בעלת מום mum עובר
*she'avda v'nimtzas ba'alas mum over*. Let's say it was lost and when
you found it, it had a transitory מום mum *mum*, a non-permanent
מום mum *mum*. Then אם אחר שכיפרו בעלים *im achar shekiperu ba'alim*,
if you found it after the owners were atoned, מתה metah. *mesa*,
then you have to or whatever you waited till you were atoned,
then you have to let it die. אם קודם שכיפרו הבעלים *Im
kodem shekiperu haba'alim*, but if it's before you brought the atonement, תרעה
עד שתסתאב *tira ad shetista'ev*. Then you have to wait until it
gets a מום mum. *mum*, במום קבוע *b'mum kavua*, wait till it
gets a permanent מום mum *mum*, ותימכר *v'timacher*, and then sell it.
So basically the way they got out of it was by redefining
the case of the מום mum, *mum* to be a temporary מום
mum, *mum*. And therefore your question was, what does it mean wait
for it to get a מום mum *mum* if the only case
you're talking about is with a מום mum. *mum*? And the answer
is, oh, we're talking about a temporary מום mum, *mum*, and when
we say wait for it to get a מום *mum*, we mean
wait for it to get a permanent מום *mum*. We still don't
know what עיבור שנה *ibur shnaso* is then. Well, that's what רבא
Rava *Rava*'s going to finally say. אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, so
רבא Rava *Rava* finally gets a little fed up and he says,
שתי תשובות בדבר *shtei teshuvos badavar*. There are two answers to this,
two responses. חדא *Chada*, דאם כן ישמר מיבעי ליה *d'im ken yishmar
miba'ei lei*. If it already had a מום *mum* and you're just
waiting for it to be permanent, then it should not be just
wait for it to get a מום *mum*, it should be observe
it to determine, you know, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says observe it to
see maybe the מום *mum* will become permanent, or תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*
says observe it maybe the מום *mum* will go away, but it
should have used a different language if it already had a מום
*mum* and the only question was whether it was temporary or permanent.
Number one. Number two, more to the point, ועוד שעיבור שנה למאי
הלכתא קתני *v'od she'ibur shnaso l'mai hilchasa katani*? That's the real question.
The way you've just read the משנה mishnah *Mishna*, you've completely cut
out the case of more than a year old. Right? The משנה
mishnah *Mishna* says the first three cases it definitely dies. Then if
you have more than a year old or lost and a מום
*mum*, then it depends if it's found, you know, when you got
the atonement whether it dies or not. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish.
*Reish Lakish* said no no no, that last discussion is only about
being lost and having a מום *mum*, not about the more than
a year old. So then there's no הלכה halacha *halacha* about more
than a year old. It's not part of the first three, it's
not part of the last one, it's just sticking out there in
the middle. So what's the point in the משנה mishnah. *Mishna*? So
למאי הלכתא קתני *l'mai hilchasa katani*? אלא Ella, אמר רבא Rava הכי
תני *Ela amar Rava hachi tani*. If you want to preserve ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish*, here's how you have to read the
משנה mishnah. *Mishna*. עיבור שנה ואבדה *Ibur shnaso v'avda*. Either it that
when the משנה mishnah. *Mishna* speaks about a case where more than
a year old will be תמות tamus. *tamus*, right, and ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* said it's not תמות tamus. *tamus*, that's when
it's not just more than a year old, but it also was
lost. It's similar to the case of the בעלת מום *ba'alas mum*.
It was lost. You combine that status. עיבור שנה ואבדה *Ibur shnaso
v'avda*, או אבדה ונמצאת בעלת מום *o avda v'nimtzas ba'alas mum*, אחר
שכיפרו הבעלים מתה metah *achar shekiperu haba'alim mesa*. קודם שכיפרו הבעלים תרעה
עד שתסתאב ותימכר *Kodem shekiperu haba'alim tira ad shetista'ev v'timacher*. It then
depends if it was if they brought their atonement, it dies. If
they haven't brought their atonement, it gets... you need three things. So
now... well, not really three, you need... I mean, here's what we're
saying. This is quite shocking again, if you always, you know, if
you know that there are these five חטאות chataot. מתות *chatasos mesos*,
so עיבור שנה *ibur shnaso*... So first the משנה *Mishna* says that
עיבור שנה *ibur shnaso* is not enough by itself. It needs that
the owners were נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher *niskaperu b'acher*. Then ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish* seems to say that עיבור שנה *ibur shnaso* is always
not really a problem and you can always let it graze and
redeem it and so on. So how do you deal with the
משנה *Mishna*? So what we really have is, is there's really just
a subset of the הלכה halacha *halacha* of נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher
*niskaperu b'acher*. When do you say נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher *niskaperu b'acher*?
First thing is it has to be lost. Okay? The next הלכה
halacha *halacha* and the next thing is not only was it lost,
but there's an additional problem. What's the additional problem? It's also a
בעלת מום *ba'alas mum* or it's also over a year old. So
there's some additional problem that means that it cannot... be brought, in
addition to the fact that it's lost. In both of those cases,
right, it was lost and it has some other problem that makes
it not able to be brought, then if you
were to תמורה temurah, and נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher מתה.
metah. If you weren't תמורה, then you can wait until you can
redeem it, right? It is three, but both of them are three.
It's not different than the five. Okay. So what it's this is
important because this is a שם, shem, meaning normally we assume נתכפרו
באחר nitkapru b'acher means, you know, first normally we assume עבר שנה
avar shanah is by itself enough to be מתה, metah? and נתכפרו
באחר nitkapru b'acher. by itself is מתה. metah So first of all,
נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher. is not by itself for מתה metah. in
the גמרא, Gemara right, as we're going to see anyway, it's going
to be a מחלוקת machloket רבי Rebbi and רבנן, Rabbanan, but certainly
for example, I'll give you a simple case that everybody agrees that
נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher is not מתה. meisah. I sanctified two animals
at the outset for my חטאת chatat. in case one is lost,
I'll have the other one available. Okay, that's what I did. And
then I bring one. The other one does not have a status
of נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru b'acher. When from the very beginning they were
both sanctified to be used, the other one you wait for it
to get a מום and you use the money for an עולה.
olah. That's that. So it's not every case of נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru
b'acher, But our משנה is saying, so what puts it in the
category of נתכפרו באחר nitkapru b'acher that everybody agrees is מתה? meita.
That it's lost, that you have a replacement, and not only was
it lost, there's another problem that makes it not able to be
brought, like it has a מום or it's more than a year
old. Then it's found, and even after now that it's found, it's
not really like it's an alternative here. It was both out of
the picture, it was lost and it can't be brought. In that
case, if you used when you use the other one, this is
נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru b'acher. So what it winds up is that עבר
שנה avar shanah is not a category by itself, it's a subset
of נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru b'acher, and נתכפרו באחר nitkapru be'acher, at least
in some cases requires a double problem: lost and another reason it
can't be brought. Yeah. You said if it was קדשים kodashim it
has to be left to die, right? If it was if something's
קדשים. kodashim. חטאת המתה. chatat hametah. Well, no, if it's in the
category of חטאת המתה, chatat hametah, if it's in the category of
these חטאות. chataot Oh, I see. Yeah. Not when they sanctified two.
That second one doesn't die, it's קדשים, kodashim, right? But then you
wait for it to get a מום and use the money for
an עולה. olah. So in the what do we פסק pasken like?
Is it? I don't know, I'd have to check the רמב"ם. Rambam.
I mean, פסק pasken for קדשים kodashim don't want to do that
as the רמב"ם. Rambam. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, וצריך. v'tzarich. Now we're going to say, okay, וצריך למתני
אם אבדה גבי בעלת מום וגבי עבר שנה. v'tzarich l'matni im avdah
gabi ba'alat mum v'gabi avar shanah. And now you have to say
since basically more than a year old is just a parallel to
בעל מום, ba'al mum, you have to give both categories. Why do
you have to give both categories? For the following reason. ואי תנא
גבי עבר שנה, v'i tana gabi avar shanah, if it had just
said by more than a year old, הוי אמינא התם הוא דמהניא
אבידה, hava amina hatam hu d'mahanya aveidah, that's where you combine it
with being lost and it leads to the category of dying. Why?
משום דלא חזיא למילתא, mishum d'lo chazya l'milsa, because more than a
year old is like completely irrelevant now for a חטאת. chatat. חזיא
למילתא chazya l'milsa is different than a phrase it's going to use
in a minute which means can't be brought. It's not that it
can't be brought, a two-year-old sheep can be brought for a different
קרבן, korban, but it's completely irrelevant to the category of חטאת. chatas
So that might put it in the category of complete irrelevance and
therefore make it easier to be considered, you know, rejected and נתכפרו
באחר. nitkapru be'acher So therefore, אבל בעלת מום,
aval
ba'alat
mum, if it was just a בעלת מום, ואי לאו מומא חזיא,
v'i lav muma chazya, that if it were not for the מום
it would be fit, אימא לא מהניא ליה אבידה, eima lo mahanya
leh aveidah, maybe being lost doesn't lead to it to die. Now,
of course, the point is if it weren't for the מום. You
know, but the point but as the גמרא Gemara said before, if
you might remember, there's all these discussions about things that might be
worse than a בעל מום, ba'al mum like a טרפה treifah or
whatever, and the גמרא Gemara considered that בעל מום ba'al mum. was
more a, you know, in Greek philosophy they had an idea of
accidental characteristics and essential characteristics of an object. So, you know, פסול
הגוף, psul haguf, which means so something is just it happened, like
the table happens to be painted red, but it's not part of
the identity of the table as opposed to like an essential characteristic,
you know, like a red table. So the גמרא Gemara seems to
feel that by other things are considered פסול הגוף, psul haguf, מום
is considered more like an accidental thing. Yes, it has a מום
now and it can't be brought, but that's not so much about
sort of the whole identity of it as an animal as opposed
to being two years old, it's a different animal now that it's
two years old. Which is true, because you have an איל ayil
and a כבש, keves, right? Exactly. Well, that's true. So anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: we're assuming, anyway, by the
way, I'm reading all of this like רש"י, Rashi, maybe in a
minute I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says, but we're assuming that,
you know, if it's lost in order to be מתה meita, and
נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru be'acher. it has to be lost plus another problem.
But the other problem has to be a serious problem, it has
to sort of seriously push it off and say that it's irrelevant.
So the
גמרא Gemara says if it
had just only indicated more than a year old, that really makes
it, that's a real case of irrelevance. But a מום, I would
have seen that as not essentially, you know, a re-identity, a different
identity of the animal, and maybe it would not have been enough
to say that it's מתה. meita, So that's why that way. ואי
תנא גבי בעלת מום, v'i tana gabi ba'alat mum, if you had
just said by the case of the מום, and you had that
plus the fact that it was lost, התם הוא דמהניא אבידה, hatam
hu d'mahanya aveidah, that's where combined with אבידה aveidah to say it
dies, משום דלא חזיא להקרבה, mishum d'lo chazya l'hakravah, because with the
מום you can't bring it for any קרבן, korban, although the problem
might be seen as more like of an accidental status problem, but
the reality is it can't be used for any קרבן. korban. אבל
עבר שנה, aval avar shanah, but more than a year old... more
than a year old although that's more about its identity but דחזי
להקרבה dechazi lehakaravah it can be brought for a different קרבן korban
not this קרבן korban a different קרבן korban אימא לא דהני ליה
אבידה eima lo dahni lei aveidah maybe it doesn't join together with
אבידה aveidah to say that it's rejected. צריכא tzricha therefore you need
both cases.
Okay, so according to רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi, basically says like this,
right? There's normally, now we have learned by the way, נתכפרו בעלים
באחר nitkapru be'alim be'acher doesn't apply to all cases, and also that
there really isn't a category, at least according to ריש לקיש and
the way we seem to be approaching it, there really isn't a
category of עיבור שנה. It's really sort of similar to בעל מום.
ba'al mum Okay, and the הלכה halacha is that even when you
say נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru be'acher. it's only when combined with certain things.
What are those certain things? That it was lost plus another problem.
The other problem is it's a מום or the other problem is
that it was more than a year old. And in those cases,
even if it was found and you brought another one, that's going
to be the case. Now by the way, I should say, I
don't want Michael you to be bothered by this, but I'll just
say for the record, I don't want to try to go, I'm
not going to go explain how the גמרא Gemara works consistently according
to this, that תוספות Tosafot reads that the extra problem actually is
more of a reason to say that it was kosher and that
the חידוש chiddush is that even with the extra problem it's still
תמות. tamus. Not that you needed the extra problem in order to
be תמות. tamus. So if that confused you, just ignore it. Anyway,
you should be aware that there's another read of this גמרא Gemara
with different גרסאות girsaot as well. Now we go on. The גמרא
Gemara says like this, אי הכי ei hachi you're not allowed to
have it. Does everyone agree that נתכפרו באחר nitkapru be'acher is in
and of itself its own problem?
Well no, not all cases of נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru be'acher The other
extreme is you sanctify two animals from the beginning for a חטאת
chatas and you bring one. There everybody agrees you use the money
for an עולה. olah. Okay, that's one extreme. The other extreme, that's
everybody agrees that that case is not מתה. mesa. The other extreme
is that it was lost and you actually brought the other one
and you were זורק הדם zorek hadam and then you found it
after it was נתכפרו באחר. nitkapru be'acher, Everybody agrees that that is
נתכפרו באחר nitkapru be'acher? even without the extra problem. The very fact
that you found it after you had already been atoned for the
other one, that makes it נתכפרו באחר nitkapru be'acher just if it
was purely lost. Right, and I want to be clear again,
all these needs of combining problems is only because of these middle
cases, right? If you had both from the very beginning set aside,
it's not, everybody agrees the other one you use the proceeds for
an עולה. olah. If you had the other one out of the
picture until you were
fully נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru b'acher. everybody agrees that it is, that it's
תמות. tamus The debates are, the debates are, yes, I'm answering,
the debates are when it is found, it only got designated after
a new one after the first one was lost, okay? They weren't
both in the picture to begin with. One was out of the
picture, but the other one was found not after the atonement, it
was found before the atonement. So what is the status of the
one that was lost and now found again? Does it remain rejected
or not? And that's where there's a debate of רבי Rebbi and
the רבנן Rabbanan that we're going to see. And that's where according
to this, you, if even if normally you said that might be
okay, if it has a double problem, it is going to be
תמות. tamut? And that's what we're talking about in these middle cases.
So let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. ומי
אמר רבא הכי? Umi amar Rava hachi? Did Rava really say that?
והאמר רבא Veha'amar Rava אבידה דלילה לאו שמה אבידה. aveidah delaila lav
shemah aveidah. So if something is lost at night, it's not really
lost. What does that mean? You can't bring a קרבן korban at
night. So let's say my חטאת chatat was lost at night and
I found it the next morning, I found it in the middle
of the night. So the period it was lost for before daybreak,
the period it was lost for was not a period of that
it could have been brought. So it's not even considered like it
was really lost. So there was really no time where the fact
that it was lost meant that it couldn't be brought. It was
nighttime anyway, it couldn't be brought anyway. So presumably that means that
even if, you know, let's say it was lost at night and
let's say it had one of these, I don't know, additional problems,
you know, it was a בעל מום ba'al mum or something like
that, whatever it was, it would still not have that הלכה, halacha.
it would not be, not be תמות tamut? because it was lost
at night. It was at a time when it was irrelevant. So
the גמרא Gemara says, doesn't that prove that the more that an
animal is not fit for the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the less it matters
that it's lost? Meaning this is sort of like תוספות's Tosafot argument
against רש"י, Rashi that the more problems actually the better it is
because if it's already irrelevant to being brought as a קרבן, korban,
who cares that it's lost? And how does it sort of get
this status of נתכפרו באחר? nitkapru b'acher, In a way, maybe נתכפרו
באחר nitkapru b'acher, requires that it have the potential to be brought
and it wasn't brought. So that's what the גמרא Gemara understands. If
you say אבידה דלילה aveidah delaila is not a problem because it
was at a time when it was irrelevant, so also if it's
אבידה aveidah and it's a בעל מום baal mum. it should be
a problem, or אבידה aveidah and it's a עבר שנה avar shanah
it shouldn't be a problem. The fact that it was lost is
irrelevant, it couldn't be brought anyway. Okay, that's at least how the
גמרא Gemara understands, compares those. So don't you see that if it's
irrelevant it's not a problem? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא דמי,
lo dami, no, it's not similar. אבידה דלילה לא חזיא לא לגופה
ולא לדמיה. aveidah delaila lo chazya lo legufa velo ledamei. At night,
it's completely irrelevant, this idea of bringing a קרבן. korban. You know,
you couldn't bring the animal itself, you couldn't used the proceeds. The
whole קרבן korban is, the whole animal, the whole concept of קרבנות
korbanot is completely off the table at night. Like my מעשר maaser
at night, right? Well, yes, but at the idea of at least
if it's relevant to be brought. אבל האי, Aval hai, but this
case where it's let's say more than a year old or it's
what do you call it, or it's מום, נהי דלגופיה לא חזיא,
nehi d'legufia lo chazya, it might not be fit to bring the
thing itself, אבל לדמי חזיא, aval l'dmei chazya, it's fit for the
value and therefore it's not irrelevant. So therefore what you have is
the following interesting idea which is: if something is, right, completely on
the one hand, if it is fit as an alternative, it's less
חמור. chamur. If you find it and it didn't have a מום
and you have both of them, then maybe it's not חמור chamur
because you could have easily have brought that. If it's completely irrelevant,
like it's nighttime where it's completely irrelevant, it's also not חמור chamur
because it's out of the picture. The only time that it's sort
of in the picture enough but bad enough to be חמור chamur
is it has these double problems. Okay, where it's got was found
and lost and it's either a more than a year old or
בעל מום. baal mum But if it's completely irrelevant like it's night
and it's out of the picture, it doesn't lead to a status
of חמור, chamur, and if it is possible to really be brought,
like it was found and you haven't brought the other, it was
found and the thing didn't have a blemish, right, then actually it
might also not be חמור chamur because then actually it's an equal
alternative. Okay, so it's very, you have to get it like right
in that sweet spot in the middle. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Need a chart here. Yeah, I know. Okay,
תנן, Tnan, okay, let's take a look. I don't know, maybe I'll
write something on the board if I had a marker, which I
don't. Okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, תנן, Tnan, okay, let's take a look. השני ירעה עד
שיסתאב וימכר ויפלו דמיו לנדבה. Hasheini yiraeh ad sheyistaev v'yimacher v'yipelu damav
l'nedava. So our, so in יומא Yoma they have a lot of
these cases of חטאת תמות, chatat tamut, or they have fun cases
in יומא Yoma where you had the two goats, right, and they
have to be taken together and then one of them dies. And
now you need the other one, now you need the other one,
but you have to do the lottery again. So you bring two
more and you do the lottery because you need to do a
lottery, you need to bring two, you can't just bring one. Okay,
so then you bring the lottery, so what do you do with
the, then you have an extra goat here, right? So what are
you going to do with it? So that's basically a חטאת שנתכפרו
בעליה באחר, chatat shenitkapru baaleha b'acher, okay, that you had the atonement
through something else, except that it's a ציבור tzibbur and not a
יחיד yachid and you don't have חטאת המתה בציבור. chatat hameita b'tzibbur.
Okay, so let's take a look what it says. השני ירעה עד
שיסתאב וימכר ויפלו דמיו לנדבה. Hasheini yiraeh ad sheyistaev v'yimacher v'yipelu damav
l'nedava. So the second one, which is the one you're not using,
question whether it's the second one of the first group or the
second one of the second group, but anyway, the one you're not
using, you wait for it to be a blemish and you use
the money for an עולה. olah. לפי שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. Lefi
she'ein chatat tzibbur meita. So a חטאת ציבור chatat tzibbur doesn't die,
so when you have a חטאת chatat that you can't use, it
doesn't die, you use the proceeds for an עולה. olah. So the
גמרא Gemara says הא דיחיד מתה. Ha d'yachid meita. So if it
were a case of a יחיד, yachid, the הלכה halacha. would be
it would die. ואמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, now which one
of the two, which one are you using? Are you using the
second one from the first group or the second one from the
second group? ואמר רבי יוחנן בעלי חיים נדחים, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan baalei
chayim nidchim, that even when the animal is alive, it can be
rejected. So the first animal of the first pair died, it's מת,
met, the second one of the first pair was rejected, right, it
was pushed away. So you're not going to use the מת met
of the first pair, you're only going to use the, so you
take a second pair, you use both of the second pair. So
when we say you wait for it to get a blemish, we
mean the remaining one from the first pair. וכשנתכפר, U'kshenitkaper, therefore when
you're going to atone with this second group, בשני שבזוג שני נתכפר.
bishni shebezug sheini nitkaper. You use the second one of the second
group. The first one was already rejected. Okay, so now what do
you have? Meaning here's the הלכה halacha? then, let's conceptualize it. So
the first, one animal of the first two died. So that meant
the second one was called a נדחה. nidcha. It was pushed away,
okay, it was sort of like we would analogize it to a,
right, we'd analogize it to let's say a בעל מום ba'al mum.
or עבר שנה, over shana, which is exactly my point. It's something
that now can no longer be used, okay. Then you bring another
group and it's נתכפרו באחר. So now you have a נתכפרו באחר,
this is a case of being a נדחה, nidcha, which is like
an עבר שנה. over shana. How do you explain why you, and
it says that what is by, it implies that were it by
case of a יחיד, yachid, it would be מתה. mesa So why
is that a question? Let's take a look. ואידך קמא הוי ליה
כי עבר שנה. V'idach kama havei lei k'over shana. Let the first
one be like עבר שנה. over shana. וטעמא דציבור, V'taama d'tzibbur, and
the only reason that you use it for an עולה olah is
because it's קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. הא דיחיד, Ha d'yachid, if it
was an individual, מתה, mesa, it would die. Now why is that
a problem? It's a problem because you have one problem and it
leads to מתה, mesa. not two. And ריש לקיש should have been
saying that when it's עבר שנה, over shana, there's really a question
to ריש לקיש. When it's עבר שנה, over shana, you need it
to combine with the idea that it was אבודה, avuda, that it
was lost. So here you have an animal that just can't be
used, it was נדחה, nidcha, you brought another one, and that's sufficient
to make it נתכפרו באחר, and we don't have the need for
a double problem. Like we said before. How do you explain that?
Let's take a look at what רבא responds. So, אמר לך רבא,
amar lach Rava, so רבא will say that to you, דחויין לחוד
ואבודין לחוד. duchuyin lachud va'avudin lachud. דחויין duchuyin being pushed away is
different than being gone. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama let's read this and
understand it. אבודין דעתיה עילויהון דילמא משתכח. Avudin daiteih ilaihon dilma mishtachach.
If something is lost, you haven't completely sort of put it out
of your mind, you're still hoping that you're going to find it.
דחויין לא הוי מתחזין. Duchuyin lo havei mitchazin. If something is pushed
off, you know it's, you know that you're never going to find
it again. Now the funny thing is, is that so what? If
it's over two years old, two years old you also know you're
never going to use it again. Right? I mean now you could
try to say the scenario is that it got a מום or
it became two years old once after it was lost, not beforehand.
But it really doesn't explain it so well and רש"י Rashi really
says you're right. Since this really remains a, the גמרא Gemara really
is only רבא is only really protecting his idea by the בעל
מום. ba'al mum, By the בעל מום, ba'al mum. that's not as
intrinsic of a problem as נדחה nidcheh or as two years old
and that needs the double problem of being lost. By something like,
you know, being נדחה nidcheh or being over a year old, that
would be a problem by itself. רש"י Rashi says you're right, this
answer in the end does not help you to explain any case
other than the בעל מום. תוספות Tosafot disagrees, let me just check
תוספות Tosafot again. תוספות Tosafot doesn't like the fact that we would
reject ריש לקיש. I guess that means הלכה halacha? is... Yeah, that
basically he's right, says the same point. That the same point that
רבא distinguishes between אבודין avudin and דחויין, duchuyin, ריש לקיש would distinguish
between more than a year old and דחויין. duchuyin. דחויין duchuyin is
like an active פסול. psul. More than a year old, okay, even
if it couldn't be used for one קרבן, korban, in theory maybe
it could be used for another קרבן. korban. So basically the way
תוספות understands the conclusion, and I know this is getting very complicated,
is that when do you say נתכפר באחר? nitkaper beacher? So either
you need, I'll try to make it a little simple, when do
you say נתכפר באחר nitkaper beacher means תמות? tamut, You either need
to be two medium-sized problems or one big problem. Okay? So medium-sized
problems are basically lost, that's not such a big problem because you
hope to get it back. A מום is conceptually not so large
because it's seen as non-essential. More than a year old is not
so large because in theory it could be used for something else.
So if you basically have, you know, two of those together, actually
it's interesting, what if you have a מום and the other thing?
I don't know. Anyway, but if you have those like combining, then
it would be נתכפר באחר. nitkaper beacher. If you have a big
problem like דחויין duchuyin where it's ממש mamash pushed off, then that
would be נתכפר באחר nitkaper beacher by itself would be enough in
that case. Okay? Getting quite confusing. Let's keep on going. I will
try to make some chart if I would have had a marker.
Let's take a look, גופא. gufa. You can do it in your
blog. Maybe if I have time. Let's take a look כ"ז עמוד
ב'. chaf-zayin amud bet. גופא, gufa, אמר רבא. אבודה דלילה לא שמה
אבודה. Avuda d'leila lo shema avuda. Lost at night isn't considered lost.
אליבא דמאן? Aliba d'man? According to whom is this relevant? אילימא אליבא
דרבנן, Ileima aliba d'rabbanan, מאי איריא אבודה דלילה? mai irya avuda d'leila?
אפילו אבודה דיום נמי? Afillu avuda d'yom nami? דאמרי רבנן אבודה בשעת
הפרשה רועה. D'amri rabbanan avuda b'sha'at hafrasha ro'eh. We're about to see
in the next משנה that if something was lost, right, this is
what I said before. What's the הלכה halacha. if it was found?
It was found after you brought the קרבן, korban, everybody agrees it's
מתה. mesa, But it was found before you brought the קרבן, korban,
you had sanctified another one but it was found before you brought
the other one, then the רבנן rabbanan actually say that it's not
מתה meisa, and you can choose which one you want to do.
Okay? So the phrase there is אבודה בשעת הפרשה רועה. avuda b'sha'at
hafrasha ro'eh. If it was only lost when you designated the other
one, but not when you brought the other one, before you brought
it you have found the first one, then the הלכה halacha is
not that it died but that you let it graze. So according
to the rabbis, right, as long as you find it before you
bring the other one, you're okay. So when you say oh but
it's only lost at night it's not a problem, well according to
the rabbis that's obvious because if you know, even if it was
lost during the day it's not a problem as long as you
found it beforehand. All right? So, and so, אלא אליבא דרבי. ela
aliba d'Rebbi. So according to רבי Rebbi that says even if it
was you had just designated, sanctified the other one, it's still going
to be a problem. התם הכא אמר רבי, Atan hacha amar Rebbi,
אלא אבודה דיום. ela avuda d'yom. When does רבי Rebbi say that
if it was lost and you sanctified another one and then found
it, it's a problem, it's תמות? tamus If it was lost at
the daytime. אבל אבודה דלילה, Aval avuda d'leila, אפילו רבי מודה דלא
אזלה. afillu Rebbi modeh d'lo yazla. But if it was only lost
at night and found before daybreak, then even רבי Rebbi agrees that
it grazes. Okay? So רבי Rebbi basically says even if it was
lost and you sanctified another one and then found, the other one
had been designated in its place and it's a problem. But if
that whole thing occurred at night, since the other one's status really
wasn't that of loss, so let's say it wasn't lost, let's say
I had one חטאת chatat here and I said you know what,
I'm afraid that something might happen to that one, I'm going to
sanctify another one. You ממש mamash sanctify two and they were both
in front of you. So that's why I said everybody agrees in
that case that even if it's נתכפר באחר, nitkaper beacher, since they
were both in front of you and you sanctified even sequentially but
they were both in front of you, that the other one is
not תמות, tamus. you use the proceeds for an עולה. olah. So
the גמרא Gemara says if that's true according to רבי Rebbi even
when it's at night and you sanctify the other one... And you
find it before daybreak, it's essentially considered like they were both in
front of you. Because the other one wasn't absent at any significant
time. And therefore, if therefore it would not be תמות tamus. even
when you bring the other one as a קרבן. korban. One minute.
So the גמרא Gemara. says like this: So, so then even רבי
Rebbi agrees. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, if you want, לעולם le'olam it's
according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, והכא במאי עסקינן באבודה בשעת כפרה. v'hacha
b'mai askinan ba'avuda b'shas kapara. And we're talking about that not only
was it lost at night, but it remained lost until you actually
brought the other קרבן. korban. Okay, so why should it matter if
it was originally lost at night? But according to the רבנן, Rabbanan,
if you find it before you bring the other one, it's never
going to be תמות. tamus. So we assumed what you bring the
other one, you bring it in the day, right? So we assumed
according to the רבנן Rabbanan that since the only... okay, now I'm
getting confused myself. Hold on. Really need to be writing this down.
Okay, anyway, so he said that if it's lost at night, it's
not a problem. So, so the רבנן Rabbanan say, look, it's never
a problem if you find it before, if you find it before
you bring the other one as a קרבן. korban. Now, if you
found it and therefore... right. Right. So we had assumed that when
we said if it's lost at night it's not a problem, it
means that it was found before daybreak. So the only period in
which it was lost was a nighttime period. And therefore you'll never
have the scenario according to the רבנן Rabbanan that you had brought
the כפרה kapara and then it was found, because you can only
bring the כפרה kapara during the day. And we assumed that when
we said lost at night is not a problem, it means it
was only lost at night. Now the גמרא Gemara is shifting and
saying even if it was just first lost at night and remained
lost during the next day, and then you brought the כפרה kapara
and so on, even that is not going to be a problem.
Because we will define its absence based on the first occurrence, not
on the fact that its ongoing is absent. And since at the
first occurrence it wasn't sort of so relevant that it was lost,
it wasn't זמן הקרבה, zman hakrava, the fact that it remains lost
is also it's not really considered lost. Okay, even according to רבנן,
Rabbanan, even if you go ahead and bring the קרבן korban the
next day. So it doesn't have to be... so meaning, I mean
this הלכה halachah about נתכפר באחר niskaper b'acher only applies when one
of them was out of the picture. If you מקדיש makdish two
animals and you brought one, then the other one you allow to
graze. So what we're saying is according to this is that if
one of them was lost at night, and since the initial state
of being lost wasn't really considered lost because it was irrelevant, it
wasn't זמן הקרבה, zman hakrava, the fact that it remains lost is
also it's not really considered lost. It's really considered like it's here.
So if it's here and I sanctify another one and bring another
one, if the other one was in front of me, it's not
תמות. tamut. You wait for it to graze and to get a
מום. The question was, hey, you know, you mentioned your scenario where
you basically מקדיש makdish both animals, right? You know, one is a
backup. But let's say I just said, well, you know, one of
these two I'm going to bring. You know what I mean? I
didn't really מקדיש makdish both. It's pretty much the same as long
as it's not אבודה, avuda, yeah. So now the גמרא Gemara, says
like this: So the גמרא Gemara says... you wait to let it
get a מום even though, even though like, you know, yeah, it's
once a... yeah. Okay, let's גמרא. Gemara אלא, so the גמרא Gemara's
says, איבעית אימא לעולם דליבא דרבנן. Iba'is eima le'olam d'liba d'Rabbanan. והכא
במאי עסקינן באבודה בשעת כפרה. V'hacha b'mai askinan ba'avuda b'shas kapara. עד
כאן לא קאמרי רבנן אבודה בשעת כפרה מתה Ad kan lo kaamri
Rabbanan avuda b'shas kapara mesa אלא היכא דאיכא אבידה ביממא. ella heicha
d'ika aveida b'yimama. When did they say if it's lost it dies?
Only where it first got lost at day. Then it's defined as
being lost. אלא הכא דאיכא אבידה בליליא. Ella hacha d'ika aveida b'leilya.
It first got lost at night, even though it remains lost during
the day, לא, lo, it would not be considered lost. So basically
again, what you've got, just to sort of remind us where we
are, is at one end of the spectrum, it's not so hard
to draw, but the marker did not materialize. Okay, if one... it
got lost. It got lost. At one end of the spectrum is
they're both in front of you, you sanctify both, nothing is lost,
then even when it's נתכפר באחר, niskaper b'acher, the other one you
wait to graze and you bring as an עולה. olah. Because if
they were never... it was never lost and was in front of
you, whatever, it doesn't have a status of נתכפר באחר. niskaper b'acher.
The other extreme is it was lost when you actually brought the
כפרה kapara and was completely lost and you were already נתכפר באחר
niskaper b'acher and then you found it. In the middle is that
it was lost and then found and then you sanctified another one
and then found. So it was not yet בזמן כפרה, b'zman kapara,
but when you sanctified the other one, the first one was already
lost. That's the case where רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan disagree,
where... Michael, you're distracting me... where the רבנן Rabbanan say it's not
there, whatever, you could look in other rooms for an עולה. olah.
Anyway, the רבנן Rabbanan say that it is not מתה, meisa. רבי
Rebbi says it is מתה. meisa And even within there, we are
number one saying maybe it only has to be lost at day,
where it's relevant to consider lost. If it's only lost at night,
then it's considered to be in this category like they're both in
front of you. And the way רש"י understands the גמרא, Gemara even
the רבנן Rabbanan that say that in this middle category it is
not מתה, meisa? will say that if there was a double problem,
if not only was it lost but it was also more than
a year old, not only was it lost but it also had
a מום, then even the רבנן Rabbanan would agree that when it
was found beforehand it would be תמות. tamut, Is that all clear?
Charlie, you look confused.
It
is confusing. No, I'm sorry, you're right. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this. Okay, so let's take a look.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, נקטינן, naktinan, we come to, we have the
following conclusion. אבידה, Aveda, now you're going to see how arbitrary it
is. Good thing Michael
left, because it's really arbitrary now. אבידה ולא גנובה, Aveda velo gnuva,
only if it's lost, not if it's stolen. If it's stolen, that
has a different הלכה. halachah Why? Because somebody knows where it is.
אבידה ולא גזולה, Aveda velo gzula, not if it's burglarized, not if
it's robbed, only literally lost. It's a very arbitrary הלכה. היכי דמי
אבידה? Heichi dami aveda? Now what constitutes being lost? אמר רבי יאשיה,
Amar Rabbi Yoshia, אפילו אחת בעדרה, afilu achas be'edra, ואפילו אחת באחת.
v'afilu achas b'achas.
Even if it's your case, Michael, even if it's mixed up in
the rest of your flock and you just don't know which one
it is. Even if it's just mixed up one with another, it's
not even like a ביטול ברוב. bitul berov. And even if it's
like right in front of you but you can't identify it, that's
considered אבודה. avuda. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, אחורי הדלת, achorei
hadelet, behind the door is considered אבידה. aveda. So what does that
mean? איבעיא להו, Iba'u lehu, היכי קאמר? heichi kama? What does he
mean? אחורי הדלת הוא דליכא דקחזי לה? Achorei hadelet hu d'leka d'kachazei
lah? Behind the door, it's only the case of behind the door
that nobody can see it because it's hiding? אבל אבראי, Aval abarai,
but if it's on the outside, דאיכא דחזי לה, d'ika d'chazei lah,
people can see it, even if it's like the case we mentioned
before, they don't know which is which, but since it's visible, לא,
lo, he wouldn't, לא הויא אבידה, lo havya aveda, it would not
be אבודה? avuda? או דילמא, Od dilma, or do you say, even
behind the
door? אחורי הדלת דמהדר אפיה חזי לה הויא אבודה. Achorei hadelet d'mahader
apei chazei lah havya avuda. Even behind the door, all you'd have
to do is turn around and you'd find it, even that's considered
אבודה avuda because as far as you know, you can't find it.
So like, oh, it's lost? No, but like you really don't know
for this moment where it is.
What kind of a question is that? If you don't know where
it is and you don't know if it's inside or outside?
Then they find it! And then you found it and then you
realized where it was, so did it have the status of אבודה?
avuda? Okay. וכל שכן אבראי דלא קחזי, V'chol sheken abarai d'lo kachazei,
and certainly on the outside where it's not easily visible, meaning, you
know, it's not easily findable. Okay, so the גמרא says תיקו, teiku,
so we don't know. So how trivial does the fact that it's
lost have to be? But is the question right now. אמר פפא,
Amar Pappa, גמרינן, gamrinan, we have a
conclusion. אבודה ממנו ולא מרועה, Avuda mimenu velo mero'eh, לא הויא אבודה.
lo havya avuda. Let's say you don't know where it is, but
the shepherd knows where it is. Okay, that's not lost. וכל שכן
אבודה מרועה ולא אבודה ממנו, V'chol sheken avuda mero'eh velo avuda mimenu,
or if the shepherd doesn't know but you know where it is,
certainly not lost. אבודה ממנו ומרועה, Avuda mimenu u'mero'eh, you and the
shepherd don't know where it is, ואיכא בסוף עולם מכיר בה, v'aka
besof olam makir bah, and somebody, you know, some stranger sees it
and presumably doesn't see it but also like knows it's yours, okay,
then what's the הלכה? מאי? Mai? So תיקו. teiku. That we don't
know. If that's considered אבודה. avuda. בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav Pappa,
Rav Pappa asks.
It's going to happen, so let's take this down.
All right, so you probably, I don't know, it's a question. What
do you do about a ספק חטאת המתה? safek chatas hamaysa? That's
a good question. Maybe you have to let it die too, I
don't know, because you can't use the money for an עולה olah
because that's a good point. All right. בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav
Pappa, so Rav Pappa asks. אבודה בכוס מאי הוא? Avuda bekos mai
hu? All right, now we, that was too easy, those last few
lines. We have to get complicated again. So now let's say it's
lost in the כוס. kos. What does it mean it's lost in
the כוס? kos? Means you already shechted it and you have the
blood in the כוס. kos. What's the הלכה? Now what is
lost? Let's take a look. אליבא דמאן? Aliba deman? אילמא אליבא דרבי,
Ilema aliba de'Rabbi, if it's according to רבי, Rabbi, meaning we assume
that it means that you found the missing animal when the blood
of the first animal was ready to be thrown on the מזבח
mizbe'ach but not yet thrown. The blood was in the vessel, it
wasn't thrown yet, and then you found the first animal. So according
to רבי, Rabbi, דאמר אבודה בשעת הפרשה מתה. hamar avuda besha'at hafrasha
meisa. He would say even if you found it before you shechted
the first animal, the animal, it's considered מתה, right? Even it was,
even if it was lost just when you sanctified the animal, it's
מתה. אלא כי מיבעיא ליה אליבא דרבנן. Ella ki miba'ei lah aliba
derabbanan. According to the רבנן Rabbis that say it's only מתה if
you find it after you were מקריב makriv the replacement. מי אמרינן
כי אמרי רבנן בשעת הפרשה רועה, Mi amrinan ki amri rabbanan besha'at
hafrasha ro'eh, when did the רבנן Rabbis say that it was found
at the time of designating, meaning prior to being brought as a
קרבן korban and the other one brought as a קרבן, korban, it
רועה? ro'eh? קודם שקיבל דמה בכוס. Kodem shekibel dama bekos. That's before
you actually caught the blood in the vessel. אבל הכא סבירא להו,
Aval hacha sevira lehu, but here they would say that once the
blood of the replacement was caught in the vessel, כל העומד לזרוק
כזרוק דמי. kol ha'omed lizrok kezaruak dami. You know, it's so close
to being brought as a קרבן, korban, all you have to do
is throw it on the altar, it's like it already happened. So
when the רבנן Rabbis say if you find the missing one after
the replacement was brought, what does it, what's the definition of after
the replacement was brought? After the blood was sprinkled on the altar
or even after it was shechted and the blood was in the
vessel? או דילמא, Od dilma, or do we say, כמה דלא איזרק
דמי, kama d'lo izrak dami, as long as the blood hasn't been
thrown, כי אבודה בשעת הפרשה דמיא. ki avuda besha'at hafrasha damya. It's
like it was only lost when the other one was designated and
it wasn't lost when the other one was brought because it wasn't
brought yet, the blood hasn't been sprinkled yet. ורועה, V'ro'eh, and it
would graze. Okay, so that's a very nice way of framing the
question.
What is the exact moment where you say the replacement was brought,
afterwards the רבנן Rabbis would say if the other one was found,
it's מתה? Was it actual blood was thrown or the blood was
caught? ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amri, some say, לעולם אליבא דרבי. le'olam aliba
de'Rabbi. It's according to רבי. Rabbi. כי מיבעיא ליה כגון שקיבל דמה
בשתי כוסות. Ki miba'ei lah kegon shekibel dama beshtei koso'os. So we're
not dealing with actually, how the, this is a fascinating translation of
the idea of אבדה. We're not dealing with two animals. We're only
dealing with one animal. But even one animal, part of it can
go missing. Which part? Some of the... But, so let's say you
caught the blood in two vessels, okay? ואבד אחד מהן ve'avad echad
mehen and you lost one vessel, okay? And you are sprinkling the
other vessel. And then you find the remaining blood. So it's sort
of like you lost the animal, you brought one, you found the
remainder, okay? אליבא דמאן דאמר aliba deman de'amar כוס עושה חבירו דחוי
kos oseh chaveiro dichui לא תיבעי לך. lo tibei lach. Now there's
a הלכה. Let's say I have all of, I caught it in
multiple vessels and I have all of them in front of me
and I sprinkled one of them. What's the status of the other
vessel? So there's a מחלוקת. machloket. Some say it's like it was
all in one vessel and the status of the other vessel is
שיריים, shirayim, the remnant of the blood that you didn't sprinkle on,
you didn't throw on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you pour at the base
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Others say no, because they were separate vessels,
each one in potential could have been the one you used to
do the עבודה avodah with. Since you picked one over the others,
you are rejecting the others. And therefore the others are not שיריים
shirayim and they don't get poured at the base of the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, they are rejected and they get poured out in the אמה,
amah, they get poured out like you know in a place where
פסולי מוקדשין psulei mukdashin go. Okay? So now that if you, so
now that's what happens to the one even if it's around that
it gets נדחה. nidcheh. So now this one was lost, okay? Now
here's the point. אליבא דמאן דאמר aliba deman de'amar כוס עושה חבירו
דחוי, kos oseh chaveiro dichui, if you say when you use one
cup the other becomes נדחה, nidcheh, לא תיבעי לך, lo tibei lach,
then there's no question that it's obviously here you know נדחה nidcheh
because it would be נדחה nidcheh even if it was around. כי
תיבעי לך, ki tibei lach, what am I asking you? אליבא דמאן
דאמר aliba deman de'amar כוס עושה חבירו שיריים, kos oseh chaveiro shirayim,
that normally if it was around the remnant would be, the other
vessel would be considered שיריים shirayim and you'd pour it at the
base of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. הני מילי היכא דאיתנהו לתרוייהו, hani mili
heicha de'itnehu letarveihu, that's if both are present, דכל היכא דבעי זריק,
dechol heicha deba'ei zarik, because if you want you could have used
the other one. And since I could use the other one, it's
potential and it's conceived as part of the, it's part of the
זריקת הדם zerikat hadam and it's שיריים. shirayim. אבל הכא הליכא, aval
hacha haleika, here it's not around. So since it's not around, maybe
even maybe even and it's absent, it's going to be considered to
be like a נדחה. nidcheh. And so now what does this have
to do with the Rabbi-Rabbanan question? But the גמרא's understanding that there's
some type of an analogy. The same way if when the animal
was absent, I sanctified another one in its stead, and therefore according
to Rabbi, even at as soon as I sanctify the other one,
this one became a חטאת מתה. chatat meitah. So here if I
have these two cups of blood and one is absent, so it's
true if it were to come back it would be part of
the process like we said before, but now it hasn't come back
yet and I'm using this. So the analogy is I'm using this,
it's like I'm sanctifying the other one, I'm choosing one over the
other, and that makes the one that's not here like a נדחה.
nidcheh. Okay? אבל הכא הליכא, aval hacha haleika, או דילמא לא שנא,
o dilma lo shana, or maybe not, we can't compare the case
of the blood with the case of the animal, so it won't
make a difference, it's still שיריים. shirayim. תיקו. teiku. Okay.
So that was part one. Now we get to see the משנה,
which is a huge משנה as you can see, and it's actually
an easy משנה thankfully, a relatively easy, and you will see that
this actually lays out the Rabbi and the Rabbanan that we've been
talking about. Maybe I'll come tomorrow with a chart to help us
understand what we just did. Okay, let's take a look at the
משנה. המפריש חטאת ואבדה. hamafrish chatat ve'avdah.
So this should have been the first משנה. You set aside a
חטאת chatat. and it got lost. והפריש אחרת תחתיה, ve'hifrish acheret tachteha,
or actually והקריב, ve'hikriv, they switch the גרסא, girsa, it's clear the
גמרא had the גרסא. girsa. והקריב אחרת תחתיה, ve'hikriv acheret tachteha,
you actually then went and brought another one instead.
ואחר כך נמצאת הראשונה, ve'achar kach nimtzet harishonah, תמות. tamut So that
everybody agrees, it dies when the first one is found after the
second has been brought. That's the Rabbanan and everybody agrees to that.
Now, המפריש מעות לחטאתו ואבדו. hamafrish ma'ot le'chatato ve'avdu.
Let's say you went ahead and you set aside money and then
it got lost. והפריש חטאת תחתיהם, ve'hifrish chatat tachtehem, and then you
brought another חטאת. chatat. ואחר כך נמצאו המעות, ve'achar kach nimtze'u hama'ot,
and then you find the money. So the money is like the
animal, it has the sanctity of a חטאת. chatat. So the same
way if it were an animal it would be תמות, tamut here
for money, what do you do with money? You have to let
the money die. What does it mean let the money die? יוליכם
לים המלח, yolichem le'yam hamelach, throw them into the Dead Sea, destroy
the money. Okay? It has the same הלכה as you would treat
the animal. המפריש מעות לחטאת ואבדו. hamafrish ma'ot le'chatat ve'avdu.
Now let's say you had the money and it got lost. והפריש
מעות אחרים תחתיהם. ve'hifrish ma'ot acherim tachtehem. Now you didn't actually, you
weren't מקריב makriv another animal, just והפריש מעות אחרים תחתיהם. ve'hifrish ma'ot
acherim tachtehem. Now
you set aside other moneys. ולא הספיק ליקח מהן חטאת עד שנמצאו
הראשונים. velo hispik likach mehen chatat ad shenimtze'u harishonim.
And now you find the first sum of money. Now what are
you going to do? If I just use one of those piles,
then the second one is a case of נתכפר באחר, nitkaper be'acher,
right?
And you're with me, it's like I have two חטאות standing here,
I'm taking one, the other is נתכפר באחר, nitkaper be'acher, at least
according to Rabbi, it would have to be תמות tamut. and I'd
have to throw it away. So don't just use one of the
piles. That's going to make the other one a rejected and a
תמות tamut, according to Rabbi. So what are we going to do?
So here's what you're going to do. יביא מאלו ומאלו לחטאתו. yavi
me'elu ume'elu le'chatato.
You mix the money together and then you bring from within the
mixture a חטאת. chatat So you don't have a specific pile that
is rejected. Now it's all one pile of חטאת chatat. money and
not, and therefore if it's all one pile, it all became one
thing, you don't have like you're picking one over the other, and
the remnant is just leftover money for a חטאת. chatat? What do
you do with leftover money for a
חטאת? chatas. יביא מהן עולה. yavi mehen olah. You bring an עולה.
olah. You make it into one object. You can do that with
money. You can't do that with...
Wait, you have to commingle the piles, right?
Yes, you do. No, you have to commingle. No, then you are
basically saying this, I'm back, I'm using this money and I'm rejecting
that money. Yeah.
No, meaning if it costs two dollars, and one dollar in this
pile... like ten cents...
like,
oh I see, you take some of the money out of those
piles maybe, maybe, right. But you can't just take from one pile,
that is rejecting the other. Okay. המפריש מעות לחטאתו ואבדו. hamaprish ma'ot
l'chatato v'avdu.
Now let's say you set aside money again and they got lost.
והפריש חטאת תחתיהן. v'hifrish chatas tachtehen. Now you have an animal, a
חטאת. chatas ולא הספיק להקריב עד שנמצאו המעות. v'lo hispik l'hakriv ad
shenimtzu hame'ot. Now you found the money. Now you've got a problem
because you want to commingle the money but you can't. One of
them is an animal. Okay, what do you do?
Really, can you...
תרעה חטאת בעלת מום.
tir'eh chatas
ba'alat mum.
So if the first חטאת chatas. has a מום, you're lucky enough
that it has a מום or maybe you wait for it to
get a מום. Then you've got a solution. תימכר וייביא מאלו ומאלו
חטאת. timacher v'yavi me'elu u'me'elu chatas. Meaning redeem it, and bring from
these and these a חטאת. chatas. Mix the money together, whatever, take
from both piles, and therefore והשאר יפלו לנדבה. v'hashar yipulu l'nedavah. And
the rest of the money is an עולה. olah. Then you're not
choosing one over the other. It's all just leftover money of a
חטאת. chatas.
Now, המפריש חטאת ואבדה. hamaprish chatas v'avdah. Now let's say it's not
that you lost the money, you lost the חטאת. chatas You set
aside a חטאת chatas and it got lost. והפריש מעות תחתיה. v'hifrish
ma'ot tachteha. Now and you set aside money. So here also the
same thing, money and an animal, except the animal is the one
that was lost, not the one that you replaced it with. ולא
הספיק ליקח מהם חטאת. v'lo hispik likach mehem chatas. You didn't buy
another חטאת chatas. with this pile of money. עד שנמצאת חטאתו. ad
shenimtzet chatato. Now you found your original חטאת. chatas והרי היא בעלת
מום. v'harei hi ba'alat mum. So again, if the one that you
found, the animal, has a blemish and you can turn it into
money, all the better. תימכר וייביא מאלו ומאלו חטאת. timacher v'yavi me'elu
u'me'elu chatas. Then sell it, then bring the חטאת chatas, from the
two. והשאר יפלו לנדבה. v'hashar yipulu l'nedavah. And the rest goes into,
and the rest goes for an עולה. olah. This is basically the
principle that money is fungible, right? So, okay, anyway, so as long
as you mix them together, then it no longer has its particular
identity. Now, let's finish the משנה. המפריש חטאתו ואבדה. hamaprish chatato v'avdah.
המפריש אחרת תחתיה. hamaprish acheret tachteha.
Now let's say you have two animals, which is going to be
really hard to get the money, turn it into money to mix
it. So you lost a חטאת, chatas you set aside another one.
ולא הספיק להקריב עד שנמצאת הראשונה. v'lo hispik l'hakriv ad shenimtzet harishonah.
Now you, and now you found the first one. Now, והרי שתיהן
בעלות מום. v'harei shteihen ba'alot mum. If you're fortunate enough that both
of them have a blemish. ימכרו וייביא מאלו ומאלו חטאת. yimachru v'yavi
me'elu u'me'elu chatas. Then sell, mix the money together. והשאר יפלו לנדבה.
v'hashar yipulu l'nedavah. It's all one thing and therefore the rest is
leftover money from a חטאת chatas. and it goes for an עולה.
olah. Now, המפריש חטאת ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה ולא הספיק להקריב עד
שנמצאת הראשונה. hamaprish chatas v'avdah v'hifrish acheret tachteha v'lo hispik l'hakriv ad
shenimtzet harishonah. Same case, two animals, no longer money. Set aside one
animal, one animal got lost, set aside another one, the one that
was lost got found. You have both of them in front of
you. והיו שתיהן תמימות. v'hayu shteihen tmimot. They're both unblemished. And either
you, and you don't want to wait a long, allow for them
to both get a blemish. Okay, or so, what do you do?
אחת מהן תקרב חטאת. achat mehen tikrav chatas. So pick one of
them for your חטאת. chatas והשנייה תמות. v'hashniyah tamut. And the second
one has to die. היא נתכפר באחר. hi nitkaper b'acher. דברי רבי.
divrei rebbi. That's what Rebbi says. So this is the Rebbi that
says that if you, even if it was lost before, even if
it was found before you brought the other one, as long as
it was lost when you sanctified the other one, that being makes
the one תמות. tamut, Now,
I should say by the way, Michael, this was a question you
asked and this actually is quite interesting. The simple sense of this
language is that according to Rebbi, you can choose which one to
bring and the other one is תמות, tamut. which is a little
funny then because then the fact that it's lost doesn't designate it
as the תמות, just creates the scenario which means that one is
going to be chosen over the other and the other is תמות.
But the very fact that it's lost would not create that reality.
Okay, anyway, וחכמים אומרים. v'chachamim omrim. I mean, we're not designating. וחכמים
אומרים אין חטאת מתה אלא שנמצאת מאחר שכיפרו הבעלים. v'chachamim omrim ein
chatas metah ela shenimtzet me'achar shekiperu hab'alim.
The only time you would say you let the other one die
is if you find it after the atonement. But if you find
it before the atonement, then you always use the other one for
the proceeds for an עולה. olah. ואין המעות הולכין לים המלח אלא
שנמצאו מאחר שכיפרו הבעלים. v'ein hame'ot holchin l'yam hamelach ela shenimtzu me'achar
shekiperu hab'alim. And the הלכה that the money goes into the ים
המלח yam hamelach is also if the money were found after the
owners were atoned. So all those cases before where things were found
before you used the other one, according to the חכמים, chachamim, you
don't have to do all that fancy mixing up the money or
anything of that stuff because as long as it was found before,
before one was brought, the הלכה is that anything leftover goes towards
an עולה. olah.
And all that mixing up the money was according to Rebbi.
Right. המפריש חטאת והרי היא בעלת מום. hamaprish chatas v'harei hi ba'alat
mum. Now let's say you set aside a חטאת chatas, and it's
בעלת מום, simple case. מוכרה וייביא בדמיה אחרת. mochrah v'yavi bidmeha acheret.
No problem. So you redeem it, you sell it, you use the
money to buy another חטאת, chatas, end of story. Now we have,
but רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר. Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon omer. אם
קרבה שנייה עד שלא נשחטה. im karvah shniyah ad shelo nishchatah. Let's
say I have this beautiful sheep, it got a מום, I set,
I sanctified it as a חטאת, chatas. I sell it there to
Michael. Then I use the proceeds, I buy a חטאת. chatas Now
I'm going, I bring my חטאת chatas, on the מזבח mizbe'ach before
Michael has had a chance to שחט shacht this thing that he
was going to use for steaks tonight. So that's true, Rebbi Elazar
bar Rebbi Shimon says an amazing thing. תמות שכבר כיפרו בעלים באחר.
tamut shekvar kiperu ba'alim b'acher. The fact that that animal that Michael
bought from me used to be a חטאת, and if I now
bring my קרבן, korban, that makes yours into a חטאת שכבר כיפרו
בעלים באחר chatas shekvar kiperu ba'alim b'acher and it has to die.
I don't know if you get a refund, maybe it's buyer beware.
So we will see about this tomorrow on פורים. Purim.